{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A member of this party earned the nickname “Sockless Jerry” in a election against J.R. Hallowell. This party nominated Thomas Watson for vice president in a temporary alliance with the Democrats. The NFAIU, a precursor to this political party, issued the Ocala Demands, calling for the abolition of national banks. This party outlined its beliefs in the Omaha Platform. The Farmers Alliance grew into, for ten points, what political party that rallied against railroads in the late 19th century?",
      "answer": "People’s Party or Populist Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty’s signing was delayed by the policy of “no war and no peace” in an attempt to buy time for more revolutions to occur. One side was forced to sign the unfavorable terms of this treaty after they were targeted in Operation Faustschlag. The Treaty of Rapallo annulled all territorial claims of this treaty, which included recognizing the independence of Ukraine and ceding the Baltic States to Germany. For ten points, name this harsh treaty, a separate peace that took Russia out of World War I.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk"
    },
    {
      "question": "The role of communism in three insurrections within this military force was investigated by the Mainguy Report. Civilians serving in this force formed the “Sheep Dog” branch during World War II. Robert Borden curtailed the funding of this force, which opponents of Wilfrid Laurier dubbed a “tin pot” endeavor. A command center of this force was destroyed by the explosion of the Mont Blanc in 1917. The Halifax dockyards once maintained, for ten points, what force that worked with the American and British navies to protect Atlantic convoys? ANSWER:Canadian Navy(promptonpartialanswers,like“theNavy”or“thearmedforcesofCanada”) (4) Photographer Cindy Sherman created a series of these works called “Untitled Film Stills.” A figure wearing a tunic adorned with the Cross of Santiago at the left hand side of Las Meninas is this type of artwork. Monkeys, necklaces of thorns, and hummingbirds appear in many of these works by Frida Kahlo, whose Broken Column was painted after she underwent spinal surgery. A bandaged ear is featured in one of these works by Vincent Van Gogh. For ten points, name this type of artwork that depicts its creator.",
      "answer": [
        "self-portraits",
        "descriptions of portraits of the artist"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the first crisis dissolved by this presidential doctrine, negotiator Robert Murphy led a delegation that carried out Operation Blue Bat, assisting the government of the Maronite Christian Camille Chamoun. The phrase “international communism” was central to this doctrine, which expanded the potential of intervention beyond Soviet-driven military conflicts. For ten points, name this presidential doctrine, first invoked in Lebanon in 1958, that was outlined by a former World War II general.",
      "answer": "Eisenhower Doctrine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this class often employed a small group of bodyguards and assistants known as a kashindan. Outcast members of this class were given the label tozama and kept under control by the shimpan and fudai. Beginning in 1642, all members of this class were required to adopt the policy of alternate attendance, strengthening control over them. Having an estate valued at 10,000 koku was needed to qualify for this title under the han system. For ten points, name these feudal lords who served under a shogun in Japan.",
      "answer": "daimyo"
    },
    {
      "question": "A raid by Robert Seales prompted this city to build the Castillo de San Marcos. In an attack on this city, Fort Mos´e was captured by forces under James Oglethorpe. After Francis Drake led a 1586 attack on this city, he sailed for Roanoke. The founder of this city massacred the nearby Fort Caroline, which had been founded by Jean Ribault and his Huguenot followers. Pedro Mend´ez de Avil´es founded, for ten points, what Florida city, the oldest continuously occupied European settlement in the United States?",
      "answer": "Saint Augustine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Willis and Nicolaus Steno independently published groundbreaking texts on these things in the 1660s. Camillo Golgi and Santiago Cajal [ca-HAL] revolutionized the study of these things through their use of a staining procedure. Hippocrates and Aristotle disagreed on the function of this object, the latter believing that they were for cooling blood. Thomas Harvey took this object from Albert Einstein without permission. For ten points, name this body part that is controversially operated on in a lobotomy.",
      "answer": [
        "brains",
        "any specific region of the brain, like prefrontal lobe after “lobotomy” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This was the easternmost state home to the possibly Crypto-Muslim Ben Ishmael Tribe. George Rogers Clark won a Revolutionary War battle at this state’s Fort Vincennes, and this state’s city of Muncie was the subject of the 1920s Middletown Studies. Another Revolutionary War hero names this state’s city of Fort Wayne. The Wabash River forms the western border of, for ten points, what state, home to the economically depressed cities of Gary and East Chicago?",
      "answer": "Indiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s transgressions were documented by Jules Marchal, whose research formed the basis of Adam Hochschild’s book [this man’s] Ghost. Gennaro Rubino tried to assassinate this man, who was granted a lease by the British on the Lado Enclave in exchange for land that they could use to complete the Cape to Cairo Railway. This ruler used the Force Publique to maintain commodity quotas in one of his colonies. The Congo Free State was the personal property of, for ten points, what king of Belgium?",
      "answer": "Leopold II"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s election to the Reichstag conveniently made him immune to Bernhard Weiss’ [vice’s] charges of libel for what this man printed in his newspaper Der Angriff, or The Attack. This man gave a speech at the Sportpalast arena in which the phrase “and storm break loose” was used to prepare citizens for total war. This man, who attempted to keep morale high by promising new “Wunderwaffen,” gave his six children cyanide pills and committed suicide with his wife in the Fuhrerbunker. For ten points, name this propaganda minister of Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Paul Joseph Goebbels"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Joseph Goebbels and this minister of armaments pressured Hitler into moving towards a war economy. This former architect became known as the “Nazi who said sorry” after the Nuremberg trials.",
        "answer": "Berthold Konrad Hermann Albert Speer"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ship of this name was towed out of Boston harbor by the Halifax after its crew locked a customs inspector in its hold to smuggle its cargo of Portuguese wine ashore. John Hancock owned that ship of this name, which was burned by defiant colonists in Newport. A group named after this concept razed Andrew Oliver’s house and met at namesake “poles” erected in colonial cities. A group that opposed the Stamp Act was called the “Sons of,” For ten points, what concept that Patrick Henry demanded, “or give me death”?",
        "answer": [
          "liberty",
          "Sons of Liberty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Liberty poles were often topped by this type of headwear, inspired by a Roman tradition. This cap often appears on Columbia, a personification of liberty, and is named for an ancient region in modern Turkey.",
        "answer": "Phrygian cap"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An old name for one of this civilization’s cities may have been “the place of the cockerel,” where chickens were bred for religiously motivated fights rather than food. The world’s first sewer systems may have been built by this civilization, whose artifacts include a bearded soapstone man dubbed the “Priest-King” and a bronze “Dancing Girl.” A place called “the mound of the dead” and Harappa were population centers in, for ten points, what Bronze Age civilization based near a namesake river running through India and Pakistan?",
        "answer": [
          "Indus River Valley civilization",
          "Harappan civilization before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Indus Valley city, whose name means “Mound of the Dead,” may have held 40,000 people at its peak. The Dancing Girl statuette was found at this site.",
        "answer": "Mohenjo-daro"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man founded the Metropolitan Club after John King was blackballed from the Union Club. This man purchased $30 million worth of New York City bonds to save the city from bankruptcy shortly after he locked bankers in his personal library until they agreed to save the Trust Company of America. This stress of being investigated by the Pujo Committee may have contributed to this man’s death. The world’s first billion dollar company was created when this man merged Carnegie Steel with several smaller holdings. For ten points, name this American financier whose bank later merged with Chase Manhattan.",
        "answer": "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "J.P. Morgan’s herculean efforts to save the New York financial system ended an economic panic in this year. To prevent a similar event, Morgan pushed for the establishment of the Federal Reserve 6 years later.",
        "answer": "Panic of 1907"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A former Permanent Representative to the United Nations named Andr´e Adam was among the fatalities in this event. Two of this event’s perpetrators had been released from prison early under the Lejeune law. Three separate attacks were carried out as part of this event, two of which occurred in Zaventem Airport and one in the Maalbeek metro station. Ibrahim El Bakraoui was among the perpetrators of this event, which occurred four months after a similar event in Paris for which ISIS also claimed responsibility. For ten points, name this March 2016 attack on the Belgian capital.",
        "answer": "2016 Brussels terrorist bombings or attack, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A week before the Brussels bombings, Belgian police carried out a raid in connection with the November 2015 Paris attacks, which targeted two separate entertainment venues that were hosting an Eagles of Death Metal concert and a France-Germany friendly. Name either venue.",
        "answer": "the Bataclan and/or the Stade de France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Cooperation with this policy was led by Mike Masaoka with the JACL. This policy was undermined by the Ringle Report, which was purposely withheld by Charles Fahy. The Civil Liberties Act of 1988 apologized for this policy and established reparation payments. This policy was supported by Executive Order 9066, which claimed to combat espionage. The legality of this practice was upheld in Korematsu v. United States. For ten points, name this World War II policy in which a specific ethnicity of East Asians were relocated to camps.",
        "answer": "Japanese-American internment"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The internment of the Japanese at Manzanar was highlighted by this photographer, who captured images of the Great Depression like Migrant Mother.",
        "answer": "Dorothea Lange"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when Thomas Foley and James Samaurez sailed the Orion and Goliath through a narrow strait between the mainland and the enemy ship Guerrier. In this battle, poorly stowed jars of paint may have caused an explosion aboard the L’Orient, where Vice Admiral Brueys died after being struck by a cannonball. Napoleon’s troops were unable to return to Europe after Horatio Nelson was victorious at, for ten points, what 1798 naval battle near the mouth of a namesake Egyptian river?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Nile accept, but do not otherwise reveal, Battle of Aboukir Bay",
          "if they give that, just give them 20 points right away"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of the Nile took place in this bay of the Nile delta. The ruins of the city of Heracleion lie submerged in this bay.",
        "answer": "Aboukir Bay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this composer’s pieces, originally excerpted from The Devil’s Deputy, was named after an object supposedly damaged in the wake of John Marshall’s death. Another of this composer’s pieces was written for a newspaper essay contest. This composer of pieces named after the Liberty Bell and Washington Post led an ensemble known as the “President’s Own,” the United States Marine Band. For ten points. name this composer of The Stars and Stripes Forever, an American known as the March King.",
        "answer": "John Philip Sousa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sousa’s Washington Post March was quoted in Central Park in the Dark by what composer, who depicted a monument to black Civil War soldiers as part of his Three Places in New England?",
        "answer": "Charles Ives"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Texan Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the Texas politician who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Became president after the assassination of John F. Kennedy.",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of San Jacinto, served as the namesake of a large Texas city, and refused to join the Confederacy.",
          "answer": "Sam Houston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran for the Republican presidential nomination in 2016 and currently serves in the US Senate.",
          "answer": "Ted Cruz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the other half of the current Texas Senate delegation and serves as Senate Majority Whip.",
          "answer": "John Cornyn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Governor of Texas for 14 years before being named Energy Secretary by Donald Trump.",
          "answer": "Rick Perry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Governor when he was shot during the JFK assassination.",
          "answer": "John Connally, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "As a vice-presidential candidate, told Dan Quayle he was “no Jack Kennedy.”",
          "answer": "Lloyd Bentsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Repealed parts of the Glass-Steagall Act with Representatives Leach and Bliley.",
          "answer": "Phil Gramm"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Czechoslovakia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Period of liberalization in 1968 in which “Socialism with a human face” was attempted.",
          "answer": "Prague Spring"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-western pact that invaded Czechoslovakia during that previous period.",
          "answer": "Warsaw Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Czechoslovakia who resigned after that invasion.",
          "answer": "Alexander Dubcek"
        },
        {
          "question": "Method of suicidal protest carried out by Jan Palach [yahn pa-lock] against that invasion",
          "answer": [
            "self-immolation",
            "description of setting oneself on fire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountainous border region demanded by Nazi Germany in the Munich Agreement.",
          "answer": "Sudetenland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writer and last president of Czechoslovakia, who opposed its breakup.",
          "answer": "V´aclav Havel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Movement that peacefully split Czechoslovakia into the Czech Republic and Slovakia in 1993.",
          "answer": "Velvet Divorce"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty between Austria and the Entente powers that created Czechoslovakia.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Saint-Germain-en-Laye"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Tibet",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Communist country that made it an Autonomous Region in 1965.",
          "answer": [
            "People’s Republic of China",
            "Zhongguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Tibet, where the Jokhang Temple was built in the 700s.",
          "answer": "Lhasa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position of spiritual leadership within Tibetan Buddhism that represents Tibet on the world stage.",
          "answer": "Dalai Lama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Current holder of that position, who fled to India after a 1959 uprising.",
          "answer": [
            "Tenzin Gyatso",
            "Lhamo Thondup"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Tibetan Buddhist text meant to guide spirits to their next rebirth.",
          "answer": [
            "Bardo Thodol",
            "Tibetan Book of the Dead",
            "Liberation Through Hearing During the Intermediate State"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of formal wear whose red and yellow types name two competing sects of Tibetan Buddhism.",
          "answer": "hat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Palace in the Tibetan capital that is the former residence of Tibet’s spiritual leaders and named after the home of a Bodhisattva.",
          "answer": "Potala Palace"
        },
        {
          "question": "1914 meeting that divided Tibet into Outer and Inner areas and created the McMahon Line.",
          "answer": [
            "Simla Convention or Accord, Agreement, etc.",
            "Convention Between Great Britain, China, and Tibet, in Simla"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1643, this country led an abortive expedition to establish a colony at Valdivia in Chile. This country lost the Battles of Guararapes, ending its brief possession of Recife that had begun with a 1630 attack on Pernambuco, part of its “Grand (20 pts)",
        "Design” strategy. This country suspended payments to a former colony after Desi Bouterse’s regime perpetrated the December Murders. The ABC Islands and (10 pts)",
        "Suriname were once colonies of, for ten points, whatEuropeancountrythatoncecontrolledArubaandCura¸caounderthenominalruleofQueenBeatrix?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of the Seven United Netherlands",
        "the Dutch Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Russell and a member of this family named Alphonso co-founded Yale’s Skull and Bones society. Under the Insular Government, a member of this family served as Governor-General of the (20 pts)",
        "Philippines. A member of this family restricted the power of unions in a bill he co-sponsored with Fred Hartley. Edward White was succeeded as (10 pts)",
        "Chief Justice by a member of this family who, 11 years earlier, had originally named White to the post. For ten points, name this political family that included Senator Robert and President William Howard."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Taft family",
        "Alphonso Taft",
        "William Howard Taft",
        "Robert Taft"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This novel’s epigraph consists of two lines from a Matthew Prior poem that compare a reluctant traveler to a reluctant hangman. This novel’s title character carries a shield with the image of an uprooted oak tree in an episode where he goes by the name (20 pts)",
        "Desdichado to express how he has been disinherited by his father, Cedric the Saxon. (10 pts)",
        "Robin Hood shows off his archery skills in a tournament in this novel, in which Lady Rowena is honored by the victorious knight. For ten points, name this novel by Sir Walter Scott."
      ],
      "answer": "Ivanhoe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of the main producers of these goods hired surveyor Gavino Guttierez to create a new site for his “Prince of Wales” brand. Production of these goods have been concentrated in locations called chichales [chee-CHAL-ays]. Because of the Ten Years War, production of these goods was moved to (20 pts)",
        "Ybor City. Workers who created these goods often paid part of their wages to a lector, who would read newspapers and other works to them for entertainment. An (10 pts)",
        "embargo on these items by JFK was partially lifted in 2016. For ten points, name this product that tabaqueros roll in Havana."
      ],
      "answer": "Cuban cigars"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eleazar Miller oversaw a famous one of these events near a mill. Manteo was the first Native American to undergo one version of this process. Kateri Tekakwitha underwent this process at the hands of the French, leading the (20 pts)",
        "Mohawk to accuse her of witchcraft. The Nauvoo Temple contains a place where individuals can conduct this process on the (10 pts)",
        "dead, an act allowed by the Mormon church. For ten points, name this sacramental process in which Christians immerse themselves in water."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "baptism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 2012 “shadow” form of this event used its original course, which George Spitz convinced Fred Lebow to replace to celebrate the American bicentennial. In 1994, G´erman Silva famously won this event’s men’s division despite taking a wrong turn, and (20 pts)",
        "Shalane Flanagan won its 2017 women’s title. Many of this event’s runners participated in relief efforts after (10 pts)",
        "Hurricane Sandy caused its cancellation by mayor Michael Bloomberg. For ten points, name this November road race through all five boroughs of a namesake city."
      ],
      "answer": "TCS New York City Marathon or NYC Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man gained fame for cautiously observing rules known as Dicta Boelcke, in contrast to his more aggressive brother Lothar. “Bloody April” was this man’s most successful month, coming while operating an Albatros D.III [d-three]. Cedric (20 pts)",
        "Popkin is generally accepted as firing the shot that killed this leader of Jasta 11, although Arthur Roy Brown, operating a (10 pts)",
        "Sopwith Camel, was initially credited. A unit nicknamed the “Flying Circus” was led by, for ten points, what German World War I ace?"
      ],
      "answer": "the Red Baron or Manfred Albrecht Freiherr von Richthofen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A riot in this city inspired a Japanese propaganda pamphlet titled “A Fight Between Two Races.” Four-year-old Tanya Blanding was killed in this city when a tank fired on her apartment building. In 1943, rumors that a woman and her child were thrown into the river caused black residents of this city to riot at (20 pts)",
        "Belle Isle Park. This city’s 12th Street Riot required Lyndon B. Johnson to send in federal troops after George (10 pts)",
        "Romney’s National Guard proved insufficient. For ten points, name this city that has historically been socioeconomically and racially divided by 8 Mile Road, the largest city in Michigan."
      ],
      "answer": "Detroit"
    }
  ]
}